Zhaolong Lu (Luke)

(312)-888 6529, lzhaolon@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Advanced data analyst with quantitative modeling skills. Having working experience on both machine learning and statistical modeling using SAS, R, SPSS and Python in Marketing and Medical Fields; Solid skills in Database Programming with PL/SQL; Hand on experience in Monte Carlo simulation and Time Series Modeling; Well-trained knowledge in, Hadoop ecosystem, Hive, Pig and Mahout, SparkR; Applied skills on data visualization using R(shiny apps, ggplot), Tableau and Gephi.

EDUCATION

DePaul University, Computing and Digital Media, Chicago, IL

Expected November, 2016

Master of Science in Predictive Analytics

DePaul University, Kellstadt Graduate School of Business, Chicago, IL

June, 2014

Master of Science in Marketing Analysis

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

INSTITUTE FOR HOUSING STUDIES-DePaul University, Chicago, United States

September, 2015 - Present

Data analyst intern ----- R, Python, Tableau

- Analyzed the margin of error and missing values of data gathering from sources internal and external
- Housing Segmentation study on 7 counties in Chicago area using clustering techniques such as K-means, K-medoids, Pam
- Anova test and boxplot plots to confirm analysis' conclusions of clusters together with geographical map
- Visualized results with geographical heat maps at census tract level using Rstudio and Tableau
- Developed Shinny app in Rstudio enabling interactive heatmap, geomap, boxplot and text input for better visualization

LOYOLA MEDICAL CENTER, Chicago, United States

March, 2015 - August, 2015

Data Scientist Intern at OnetoMap Analytics LOYOLA SURGERY ----- R, Python

- Communicated with medical students for gaining medical knowledge on dataset of 13,000 patients between years 2008-2013
- Used paired t-test to identify the differences of patients' day-night shifts given medical treatment
- Executed Chi-squared test to testify the significance of the access frequency of patients' information database
- Setting bench mark using Tree model in different criteria such as C4.5, CART and CHAID
- Compared logistic regression and tree model in classifying patients' mortality status
- Responsible for the findings that intensive health care lead by significant day-night shifts and frequent database accessing helped to decrease mortality rate

NATIONAL LEVEL DATA MINING CASE COMPETITION, Chicago, United State

April, 2016 - Present

Rang Technology and KVRA ----- R

- Goal is presenting the best binary classification from real-world data from retail industry concentrating on accuracy
- Manipulating data by permutation and removing missing value using VIM package
- Feature Engineering using random forest (BORUTA), Logistic regression with penalty (Lasso,glmnet)
- Comparing different binary classification method based on selected features

FC CONSULTANT GROUP, Chicago, United States

January, 2015 – April, 2015

Analytics of FC Consultant Group ----- SPSS

- Understand client's business expectation, identified gaps, presented quantitative analytics solutions to help clients make decisions
- Built marketing strategies based on PEST, Five Forces model, SWOT analysis, distribution analysis and competitor analysis
- Collected and aggregated raw data from different resources, manipulated data into efficient and informative format for modeling
- Developed and implemented quantitative methods to discover key factors affecting customers' attitude of purchasing
- Targeted customers by analyzing customer segmentations using k-means and hierarchical clustering methods

PROJECT EXPERIENCE

MINING BIG DATA

Analyzing Chicago Crime data using HIVE and PIG-----HADOOP

Spring 2015-2016

- Pre-setups for building multiple clusters within Hadoop environment in Linux environment
- Using PIG and HIVE queries extract data into practical analysis
- Comparing time used for single and multiple nodes under HIVE and PIG queries

TIME SERIES ANALYSIS

Autumn 2014-2015

Microsoft Stock Price Prediction-----R

- Examining the Autocorrelation and partial autocorrelation analysis of the data
- Fitting data using ARMA and GARCH model with the different distributions for Residual Analysis
- Establishing IGARCH Model to Predict the Stock Price of Microsoft

PROGRAMMING DATA MINING APPLICATION

Autumn 2015-2016

Collaborative Recommender System for Music website last.fm -----Python

- Compared standard similarity and SVD similarity from both speed and accuracy aspects
- For each similarity methods using similarity functions such as Euclidean, Cosine, Pearson Correlation to select best model
- Selected SVD method with Euclidean similarity measurement to build the recommender system

CERTIFICATE

- SAS Certified: Advanced Programmer for SAS 9; SAS Certified Base Programmer for SAS 9
- Coursera: R-The Data Scientist's Toolbox, R Programming; Python- An introduction to interactive Programming in Python;
 Bigdata and NoSOL database: Introduction to Big data